Guide to the Rockford University Microfilmed Julia Lathrop Papers, 1880-1932
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Julia Lathrop Papers, 1880-1932
1990
Lathrop, Julia Clifford, 1858-1932
6 reels
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Microfilmed set of the Lathrop Papers held by the Rockford University Archives in Rockford, Illinois.
Biographical Note
Julia Lathrop, Vassar Class of 1880, was a noted Progressive Era reformer who focused particularly on child welfare. She was born in 1858 in Rockford, Illinois, where she attended the Rockford Seminary (now Rockford University) along with Jane Addams and Ellen Gates Starr. After graduation from Vassar, Lathrop worked in her father's law office. In 1890, she moved to Chicago to work with Addams, Starr, Grace Abbott, and others at Hull House. It was the start of a long and active career in social reform. She was appointed to the Illinois State Board of Charities, became the director of the U.S. Children's Bureau, and spent her retirement years as the president of the Illinois League of Women Voters, and a member of the League of Nations' Child Welfare Committee. Lathrop died in 1932.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Subject Headings
Organizations:
Vassar College--Alumni and alumnae; Hull-House (Chicago, Ill.); Rockford College; League of Women Voters of Illinois
Names:
Addams, Jane, 1860-1935; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962; Abbott, Grace, 1878-1939; Balch, Emily Greene, 1867-1961; Beers, Clifford Whittingham, 1876-1943
Subjects:
Child welfare--United States; Social Reformers--United States
VCL Categories:
Women's History
Encoding Information
Encoded August 2015. Updated by Emma Gronbeck, November 2023.
Location of Originals
Rockford University Archives
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Microfilm reader required.
Container List
- Photograph- Julia Lathrop portrait (Reel 1)
- Photograph- award from Warsaw, Poland, 1920 (Reel 1)
- Photographs - [relatives of Julia Lathrop?] (Reel 1)
- Correspondence with Sarah Anderson (Reel 1)
- Vassar Graduation, 1880 (Reel 1)
- Hull House, 1894 (Reel 1)
- Correspondence - State Home for Juvenile Female Offenders, 1895 (Reel 1)
- Spoils System, 1895 (Reel 1)
- Correspondence with parents, 1897-1909 (Reel 1)
- Notes on Domestic Science, 1899 (Reel 1)
- Meeting of State Board of Charities, 1899 (Reel 1)
- Correspondence with Jane Addams, 1897-1922 (Reel 1)
- Correspondence, 1900 Nov-Dec (Reel 1)
- Correspondence, 1901 (Reel 1)
- Correspondence - Position in Domestic Science at Rockford College, 1902 (Reel 1)
- Miscellaneous papers, 1902 (Reel 1)
- Correspondence, 1902-1906 (Reel 1)
- Miscellaneous papers, 1903 (Reel 1)
- Miscellaneous papers and clippings, 1906 (Reel 1)
- Correspondence, 1907 (Reel 2)
- Newspaper clippings, 1907 Jan-Jun (Reel 2)
- Correspondence, 1908 (Reel 2)
- Charitable Institutions Legislation, 1908 (Reel 2)
- Correspondence with Clifford Beers, 1908-1912 (Reel 2)
- Correspondence, 1909 (Reel 2)
- Correspondence, 1910 (Reel 2)
- Committee on Occupational Standards - St. Louis Convention, 1910 (Reel 2)
- Juvenile Psychopathic Institute, 1910-1912 (Reel 2)
- Correspondence, 1911 Jan-Jun (Reel 2)
- Correspondence, 1911 Jul-Dec (Reel 3)
- Illinois Society for Mental Hygiene, 1911-1912 (Reel 3)
- Correspondence, 1912 (Reel 3)
- Correspondence, 1913 (Reel 3)
- Miscellaneous papers, 1915 (Reel 3)
- Miscellaneous papers, 1918 (Reel 3)
- Correspondence, 1920 (Reel 3)
- European voyage, 1920 (Reel 3)
- Correspondence, 1921 (Reel 3)
- Correspondence, 1922-1923 (Reel 3)
- Addams Nomination to 1922 Conference of Social Work, 1922-1923 (Reel 3)
- National Consumers’ League, 1922-1924 (Reel 3)
- Child Labor, 1922-1924 (Reel 3)
- Correspondence with William Maddox, 1922-1931 (Reel 3)
- Correspondence, 1923 (Reel 3)
- League of Women Voters, 1923 (Reel 3)
- Speaking engagements refused, 1923 (Reel 3)
- Joint Committee on Methods of Prevention of Delinquency, 1924 (Reel 3)
- Correspondence, 1924 Jan-Oct (Reel 3)
- Correspondence, 1924 Oct-Dec (Reel 4)
- Newspaper clippings - Child Labor, 1924-1925 (Reel 4)
- Speaking Engagements, 1924-1925 (Reel 4)
- Speaking Engagements Refused, 1924 (Reel 4)
- League of Women Voters, 1924 (Reel 4)
- Correspondence, 1925 (Reel 4)
- Jane Addams Social Service Chair at Rockford College, 1925 (Reel 4)
- Child Labor, 1925 (Reel 4)
- Correspondence with Eleanor Roosevelt - child labor, 1925 (Reel 4)
- Correspondence with Grace Abbott, 1925-1932 (Reel 4)
- Correspondence, 1926 (Reel 4)
- Infant Mortality, 1926 (Reel 4)
- Speaking Engagements, 1926-1927 (Reel 4)
- Correspondence, 1927 (Reel 4)
- Child Labor, 1927-1928 (Reel 4/5)
- Miscellaneous, 1927 (Reel 4/5)
- Correspondence, 1928 (Reel 5)
- Correspondence, 1929 (Reel 5)
- Correspondence, 1930 (Reel 5)
- Correspondence, 1931 (Reel 5)
- Correspondence and death of Florence Kelley, 1932 (Reel 5)
- Lathrop's death - Clippings, tributes, and memorials, 1932 (Reel 5)
- Lathrop's death- Memorial programs (Reel 5)
- Lathrop's death (Reel 5)
- Lathrop's death - Letters to family (Reel 5)
- Lathrop's death - Journal article, 1932 (Reel 5)
- Miscellaneous notes, speeches, clippings, and photographs, (5 folders) (Reel 6)
- Julia Lathrop and Rockford College (Reel 6)
- Memorabilia, (2 personal checks) (Reel 6)
- Bibliography of Lathrop items in Rockford College Publications (Reel 6)
- Case, Anne (Lathrop) (Reel 6)
- Correspondence with Emily G. Balch (Reel 6)
- Envelopes and stamps (Reel 6)
- Notebooks - miscellaneous (Reel 6)
- Book - My Friend Julia Lathrop by Jane Addams (Reel 6)
- Medals - Award given to Julia Lathrop by The National Institute of Social Sciences (Reel 6)
- Medals - The Orther of the White Lion of the Czechoslovakian Republic presented by President Masarych to Miss Julia Lathrop (Reel 6)
- Medals - 2 brown medals with images of Robert M. LaFollette. Buton K. Wheeler (Reel 6)
- Medals - Two religious medals - one with an angel image and the other with an angel and two persons, Rio de Janeiro, 1922 (Reel 6)